[Music]
welcome to the react native Show podcast
brought to you by kak a total software
engineering consultancy my name is Kuba
Urban and I am your coffee talk host
today uh I have two more guests but you
know wait for it they're are special and
I will introduce them for now I just
wanted to say that we will talk about
the state of react state of react native
and all things around it uh we're going
to talk about Journeys in the tech
industry and how it can look like for
you know everyone else basically maybe
this will inspire your journey so my
guests today um one of them is my fellow
Co Stucker Ola Ola can you introduce
yourself please yes hi so my name is Ola
this short hand for Alexandra but I
always go by Ola because it's confusing
that these two names are one name yeah
as I've been uh I've been working at
Cola for the last oh my gosh over two
and a half years and in the same project
with Kuba for for like half a year or
year or even a year maybe a very
interesting project we work on TVs
mobile phones web everything and it's
challenging and it's
fun yeah and thank you very much Ola and
I'm glad to have you here to today and
my second guest it's a special guest
because she is not from Kack and she is
from from far away uh because uh from UK
Anisha uh can you please introduce
yourself tell us something more about
what you do on everyday basis sure uh hi
guys I'm Anisha and I'm a developer
Advocate at the Amazon app store um and
usually when I introduce myself the
first question that goes to everyone's
mind is like what is a developer
Advocate um so it's kind of my job to
make it easier for all the Developers to
develop for Amazon App Store so whatever
shape or form that takes sometimes it's
writing articles sometimes it's writing
sample code sometimes it's coming on
podcasts like these um but yeah it's
it's my role just to make it easier for
you to develop TV apps um tablet apps so
anything that goes on Amazon app store
and Fir OS um but my background is react
native and my focus is on react native
apps for
firest lovely so basically whenever I
cry over my project here I should just
call you and be like hey Anisha please
help yes and I will try my very best to
help because usually one person's
problem is similar to other people so if
I can solve it for you I'm sure I'll
help other people all right all right
awesome uh so yes people as you can see
and hear uh we have a lovely team today
and uh ladies here will talk about their
Journeys uh so you know sit back and uh
have a good good listen good watch
depending on the platform um
so maybe we'll start with Anisha so
Anisha how did you start your Tech
Career like what sparked the idea what
brought you to us yeah yeah so I did
engineering um at University so I did
biomedical engineering which is very not
related to what I do now um when I was
looking for jobs I knew that I wanted to
stay in London which is probably not a
good reason to be applying for jobs but
it was it was my motivation
and I started as a technical consultant
at IBM and while I was there a lot of
the projects were react and react native
based so I would annoy the developers
into teaching me because the project
management side or the things that you
have to do as a grad were not as
interesting as what they seem to be
doing um I did have a bit of background
so I did C++ and a bit of machine
learning in uni but I think it was just
really seeing like the cool things that
the developers were building so I
learned JavaScript um taught myself
while I was on the job and then begged
someone to put me on a project that was
react and that made me learn react um so
I didn't react like front end
development for about four years and
while I was doing that a lot of things
that I was learning I felt like would
consolidate it by sharing it so I did a
few talks and that's sort of how I ended
up as Amazon as a developer Advocate um
because sharing what I knew was like a
way for me to learn more um and I didn't
even realize it was a role that existed
but here I am um and my final project at
IBM was like working on a react native
app for the last two years so that's
sort of how I got into react native but
it was definitely js's react and then
react native awesome awesome and by the
way that that role that you have right
now the the developer Advocate was it
like proposed to you because they saw
that you're good at it or was it
something that you opted for and be like
hey I want to do this stuff I think it
was a bit of both so it was like I was
looking for a new job at that time and I
think the person who hired me had seen
that I'd done some talks and one of my
talks that was like quite well that went
I don't know I wouldn't say viral or
anything but it was just like it got a
couple of views and it was like called
new kid on the blockchain and I was just
talking about like how I learned
blockchain and then I built like a react
layer on top of a blockchain yeah and I
think like he probably he saw like this
coupling of like different Technologies
and me explaining it and thought that's
like what it takes for a developer
Advocate is being able to like take
these complex problems and sort of make
it digestible but also find a way to
talk about things that might not
necessarily be being talked about so
that's sort of how I ended up at Amazon
are you are you a secret Bitcoin
billionaire if you know I wish I
wish oh I wouldn't have a radiator then
I'd
have it'll be
golden well I me at least now uh I have
a better background otherwise you would
have some kind of freaking ocean with a
beach behind
you usually when I record videos people
are like can you remove the radio I was
like no I need to stay
warm true true it's important all right
Ola how about you how did you start what
what brought you to Tech um me well I
studied something completely different
because I studed French philology and I
actually wrote a book at the end of my
studies that was like um literary
analysis type of thing uh but there's
that much work in translating French to
polish so I always liked computers and
HTML was just like the easiest thing to
learn so I started by HTML the CSS JS
then react and then react native in
short there's like 10 years of my life
in one sentence but yeah so how did you
you how did you actually stumble up the
react native like was it just random
project that you jumped in or how did it
no I was like I was like at the
beginning where like smartphones were um
were making their appearance I thought
that apps were awesome and I just played
around with anything that was possible
to be done with uh with uh JavaScript so
I start with ionic actually like I I
worked with angler the first angular um
the prehistoric one and then ionic which
sort of sucked and then I thought like
that there must be a better way and then
I found re native I saw flut on my way
but like I didn't stay long okay that's
good because of that you're with us yes
yeah yeah exactly I feel like most
developers like start with angular and
they're like nope and then they end
react native look angular had its time
you know it was very very big and
popular right like me for example I
started web development with angular um
because I I I I I had a chance to move I
started as a backend devel developer and
then I had a chance to move up to the
full stack but I had to learn angular
right uh not the first one it was the
better one already I don't remember the
specific version but yeah uh but from
there I I could go to react because I
could do the the front end right and
then I had options so that was nice but
yeah angular was there and angular like
I feel like angular was necessary to
make this step from JavaScript just
being like this jQuery making buttons
pretty thing to something more yeah that
that's what angler did for pretty much
all front and development all right all
right yeah I I mean I agree with you but
uh it's interesting to to to to see that
Ang was somewhere for everywhere
everyone not especially nowadays um all
right all right so moving on let's let's
uh let's skip a bit ahead right let's
leave the beginnings uh and jump into
the now all right so
nowadays what what do you do now
nowadays you uh maybe with Ola right now
you all mentioned that we are working on
the project together building stuff for
TVs mobiles and stuff like that um can
you say something more about your
everyday everyday tasks and and job what
what what do you prefer working on and
what do you work on how does it look
like for you uh well actually I enjoy
working on TVs it's like a special type
of challenge because what you have on
TVs and you don't have on mobile phones
are Focus uh issues because you have the
remote and you have the an item that's
that that lights up and you move with
your remote so that's always a fun
Challenge and we have like a gazillion
emulators uh that we need to work with
and well I I I like it when my job is a
little bit tough because you know makes
me think and it what I like when it's
challenging okay so that's good that's
what I like fck is management and you
love it oh my God give me
that I didn't say I love it I I said I
like it well that's Alla people that's
Alla uh okay thank you very much uh
Anisha how about you because your role
that you described it sounds like you do
a lot of different things so what do you
focus on nowadays yeah so I guess it's
my job to make ola's job easier
basically um so I actually watched like
you know your one of the last episodes
of um the PO podcast and you were
talking about yeah developing on TV and
that's basically my Focus right now is
like how to make building react native
TV apps easier or you know just
exploring like what developers are doing
right now um I think this year like I'm
really interested in seeing like how can
we test TV apps because it's such a
unexplored area I mean like in general
like developing for TV apps is just not
as talked about or there's not as much
content around it um I think recently
bam theodo they just released a Blog on
on react native TV and it's going to be
really exciting to see like the content
that comes out because like all I said
there's so many challenges when it comes
to TV that you don't see on like mobiles
or tablets
um sorry bam is actually that's okay bam
is working on like their own Focus
management Library yeah yeah I think so
um yeah in terms of testing like other
than really just and react native
testing library and a couple of the
performance tooling like there's not
much that was built with TV in mind um
so that's sort of what I want to look
into this year and Anisha do you have
like a a favorite part of your job since
you have so many jobs wrapped up in one
is there something that you like more
than other tasks H I think I would say
the the conferences like I mean that's
where I met um everyone from coack I
think you you get to meet the people who
you know you've admir like you know I
met Lorenzo and Nicola and I've been
using react native I've seen their names
pop up on GitHub and um you know the
change logs like a thousand times and to
be able to meet them and talk on the
same stage as them um was amazing and I
actually got to talk about something I
really like which is story work um so I
think that's my favorite part being able
to use the tech I like see how it might
make you know developing for Amazon
easier and then being able to share it
all right and by the way uh you can see
anisha's talking about storybook on the
conference on our YouTube channel so go
ahead and check it out it was really
really cool I loved I I loved your talk
I loveed the storytelling about it that
was so cool thank you yeah same same so
go go ahead and check it out if you
haven't yet and um oh boy uh so I can PL
plug my uh few words in here as well uh
well I I don't really enjoy working with
Focus management I'm
sorry that's okay speaking of TVs um
it's really interesting that you see you
say that it's very unexplored because it
is that's true from the technical point
of view but not only because like ux on
TV is completely different than on any
other platform as well right you need to
make users use the remote and be you
know fine with it be be nice and and int
intuitive which is not that easy uh
which brings I think another issue that
very uh often these TV apps uh they they
kind of have similar vibe to them
because you know they have the ux that
just works um but they all look like
Netflix let's just be honest like you
know
Netflix like they nailed the UI and they
everybody's just sort of trying to copy
it that's true that's true but you know
now when when we see this um this spark
of TV development and you know react
native getting there maybe we'll see
something complet completely new in in
you know couple of months couple of
years you know it everything changes so
fast um
true all right uh
So speaking of uh of
changes if we if we think about react
and react native maybe maybe let's focus
on react native for now five years ago
react native versus today's react native
do you have um you know do you have any
specific thoughts on that like we know
that
Everything Has Changed basically right
uh there were class components we can
still use them but let not uh we didn't
have hooks and stuff like that so what
what are your thoughts Anisha go ahead
yeah well I think you nailed the two
main ones um I think to understand like
the changes in react native first of all
like they stem from the changes in react
and I think the major ones were yeah
like you know the recommendation like by
react docs themselves like they updated
their docs last year and you can see
this real shifted focus of functional
components from class components and
with it obviously the recommendation
like of a hooks first approach um we've
seen the context API come into play and
I think in general like there's been a
lot of changes to how state is handled
so you know we saw context come around
in 2018 hooks came around in
2019 um and I think just the way that
you think about building your react and
I guess hence react native app has
changed a lot um I personally really
like the functional component first
approach like I never really enjoyed
class components but I still think that
they had their advantages um which we
can touch on um maybe when we go into a
little bit more detail about like the
benefits of functional versus class or
class versus function for sure for sure
we can get there uh yeah uh AA would you
like to add anything to that I mean I I
totally agree like if if we just if if
we were to look only at react native I I
wouldn't say besides all the stuff that
Chang in react not much else changed in
react native right like like you said
like all the main changes come from
react and they are huge um so if we try
to imagine what it was like to try and
learn react 5 years ago like when we
learned react and uh if we look at
someone who who would be reading the new
documentation now and reading it now
it's like a completely different Journey
uh because they they are presented with
pretty much a different product maybe I
want to say yeah like yeah it's like
it's it's a different thing it has
context it has hooks like before it was
you know just components and you have to
deal with the rest on your
own um so the the the mindset is
different I haven't like I haven't
looked at articles because I remember
like from all documentation I remember
an article that I loved about the react
mindset and it like made a great
impression on me do you know Anisha if
that article is still there yeah yeah
it's definitely still there but I I
really like as well like they've brought
a lot of those Concepts to the Forefront
like when you go into the new docs like
you see yeah thinking and react you see
like how like hooks first approach so
it's much nicer I would say learning
today is lucky because it's much nicer
yeah I mean with with the development of
all these um how to call it like
different techniques different and um
different architecture ideas and stuff
like that also the develop the
development experience improved right
the the developer experience I think at
least nowadays I'm not sure five years
ago but nowadays developer experience is
one of key factors why why people choose
react and react native to work with and
this is quite amazing like I I I don't
recall that five years ago people would
stumble upon some technology and they be
like nah this is not a great DX let's
not use it nowadays because we got so
much much to choose from people are like
focusing on this stuff and I really love
it because you know I am I'm kind of a
lazy person when it comes to like you
know working so when when something
requires me doing extra work just
because the technology doesn't allow me
to do it faster and easier I'm just so
um like not motivated you know it's just
another obstacle that comes in the way
of my creativity and passion to to to
building right and that sucks so it's
great to see that also that improved you
know could about more stuff that
improved of course but there's there
there's a trap there because you have
like new devs who only learn well
hopefully they learn JavaScript so they
have some like basic knowledge hopefully
and then they they jump into react and
they see use effects in context and then
you uh they they write websites that
suck because they don't realize about
re-rendering about the effect that using
like a wide uh like one single context
for the whole app that R renders
everything all the time or like they
don't care about uh the dependency array
and their use effects because they don't
understand why it's so important you
know so okay you can go fast it's nice
it's comfortable but then you hit a
roadblock where your app sucks and you
have to like sort of learn all the
nitty-gritty small problems and you have
to work with them I think that's so true
yeah and I think like when you came from
class components like learning about
those life cycle methods like component
did Mount component will Mount like you
had those clear entry points for like
where you'd initiate state where you'd
clean up state it was much more kind of
intuitive like to handle cleaning up
your resources setting up your resources
and like I think you know the class
components off offered like explicit
ways you know to implement when you had
error boundaries so I think when you
come from that way of thinking like
you're more likely to think about where
should I set my state up like I think
when you start yeah but when you start
functional for first you're not going to
have for example components that just
handle state or components that just are
dumb functional components yeah um so I
think that logic change it was great to
learn like when you learned class
components because now you can think
about setting up your state like from
that way of thinking yeah exactly and
the and the logic was linear like right
because you're setting up your component
it should be or not right and now for
example and you you get a you get a PR
and you see that somebody added or
changed a use effect and it's like a
th000 that that's what happens in our
project with Coley so we have a file
that's a thousand lines long somebody
adds or changes a use effect and even in
the diff you don't see the whole file so
you don't know there's like five other
use effects that sort of you know go
yeah yeah crazy I think there was a
really great talk at like a reacted
Advance London where someone was like
how to use a use effect effectively and
I really like that cuz like I was like I
relate so hard to some of these problems
like literally if you use the use effect
without the dependency you're not ever
going to realize that it's just in an
endless loop right until you for example
log it out or you you check out the
performance and you're like okay this is
like running a render every single time
um but it's such a simple thing to
forget like you just forget to put that
bracket and that's it um so I get it I
think before you were like forced to put
State Management in like the higher
order components and then you would
think logically about what that lower
level component was doing
but nowadays like it's not as I would
say for what's the right word I don't
know it's not as clear cut like you can
have a component that does like a
thousand things yeah yeah yeah but also
because the I think the process of of
developing react got easier right over I
mean yeah depends how you look at it but
let's say it comfortable for sure yeah
more comfortable and that makes you as a
fresh developer be like okay I can build
an app by just knowing this Basics
that's great but you don't realize as as
you mentioned like creating a context
that's going to wrap up your whole app
and you're going to keep your state
there for a fresh developer it sounds
like awesome I can just keep everything
there right it's it's nice and intuitive
and then you don't realize that well
your performance sucks right now and you
don't know why back in the days when you
know you had to to to build stuff uh
step by step with with as you mentioned
with um life cycle methods and all this
stuff you had to understand why you're
doing this and when it's going to be
executed and stuff like that right so
yeah if you started with class
components you probably have deeper
knowledge nowadays because you had to
transition transition to the more
comfortable environment than what you
were used to right um and not not even
mentioning the the react forget or react
compiler uh yeah it's compiler now yeah
they just announced it not too long ago
yeah they just announced it and it's it
seems like it's going to make um you
know the process even easier you will
not even have to care about like
memoization and stuff like that you know
you don't have to care about the use
memo or react do memo and stuff like
this so you know without this knowledge
question is is it good or is it not good
that it's gonna be this simple you know
we're gonna have I feel like we're going
to have so many mediocre apps or just
mediocre code everywhere um and only the
the few ones that are really good and
Polished with a deeper knowledge uh in
place right uh but yeah that I'm just
I'm just wondering here because I'm I'm
I'm really curious about the oh no pun
intended like I've seen I've seen tweets
where people are wondering if Poland is
like a hot bed for react native
development because we have call St
software mention in Poland it's
ridiculous I want to officially say we
do not have react native universities in
Poland I don't I don't know why we love
look but but Shimon from Kack uh at his
uh high school he is learning react by
like by the program so Shimon he's like
he's like a 16-year-old who works and
does open source he's just out of this
world maybe he doesn't even go to school
he just tells that yeah it's
possible you mention like op tour sorry
um to kind of digress but I think one of
the main changes in react native like I
personally have seen over like the kind
of four or five years is I mean like
Expo has made it incredibly easy to to
build those react native apps um you
know you can build for like one plat
multiple platforms from like one code
base and like deploy it much more easier
than say five years ago and I think like
that open source Community around react
native like it's it's it's way stronger
like than I would say around react and I
think that for react native is probably
one of the key changes like i' I've
personally seen is like how strong your
open source Community is MH yeah that's
yeah that's a very good point and we
have we have the like the biggest
migration is Dan abramov who moved to
Blue Sky and he's working on react
native and I guess we're all sort of
waiting for him to make our lives even
more comfortable and come up with
something great come on Dan this is a
message to you yeah clock is ticking
it's been a few months no new Redux yet
yep no new
Redux oh that's a good one all right uh
but by the way do you have any thoughts
like why the hell react native has such
a big Community like bigger than react
that's what I mean like everything
started with react like what what what
what happened on the
way where people just hungry for good
you know crossplatform functionalities
and stuff like that and they were like
all right let's do it the correct way or
what happened maybe I missed
something I I honestly wouldn't know but
I'm here for it like I I I love it I
think it makes like everyone's jobs like
a thousand times easier um I actually
made my first open source contribution
like very recently so it was actually to
your your guys's um repo so react native
testing Library uh and I think it's just
maybe it's like more welcoming like I
don't I don't know if it's more
welcoming or it is welcoming like you
meet the people working on the thing
you're using so it's easier to like feel
less intimidated to contribute um yeah
for me that was definitely for me that
was definitely a factor like to see that
the community felt smaller so I I sort
of like I I felt like I knew the faces
like that popped up on GitHub and and
Twitter and so that that does make it
less intimidate intimidating and I also
think that um on on web the the
ecosystem like the whole the the amount
of options you have to build a website
is huge compared to mobile apps that
makes sense and right we don't have that
many options for for good mobile apps
and so they're just like when you take
the
percentage you know yeah yeah and the
and the nice side effect of that
Community Driven technology is well
conferences you get to meet all these
people face to face like I remember
working with DOT net a lot back in the
days and you know doet is is is a big
nice technology but it's curated by the
huge company right it's not it wasn't
open source back then and
I remember that you know every
conference was you know meeting nice
people of course but these people are
just random people working with this
technology not working on the technology
which is so much uh different experience
than when you go to the reactnative
let's say reag native EU last year right
you were there hope you were there and
it was so much fun to just see those
people who you know as those Legends of
react native and it turns out these are
actually normal nice people you know you
can hang out with them this is so cool
yeah all right all right so you know
let's let's tackle this how you would
compare learning react uh SL reactnative
back in the days right uh when you
started to like newcomers nowadays um
and I'm talking here about you know
some maybe not specifically challenges
but different approaches right when when
we started there was there were class
components for example nowadays you
start off by learning that there we
class components but don't use them
there are functional components now
right so stuff like this do you do you
have any thoughts on that if I can but
in like the worst thing I see on Reddit
is people saying I don't I don't know
JavaScript and I'm trying to learn react
native and I see that post and I just it
it's just you're setting yourself up for
disaster anybody please learn everybody
please learn react native but please
start with like at least some basics of
JavaScript you can go to W3 schools some
people love it some people hate it but
at least you know something to to have
like a basic understanding of JavaScript
and then go ahead and dive into some
react and then react native and that
that that's a good path that's the same
path that we took five years ago it's
the same path now except with better
dogs that look better yeah and they're
great shout out to Rachel and Dan for
that especially yes yes definitely but
yeah I really like your your comment a
lot that you know start start with
Basics right and um it's interesting
because you can learn react and react
native without knowing javascri I mean
it's possible it's just not
gonna don't yeah but just just don't do
that you know like imagine you trying to
build I don't know build a wooden table
but you don't know how to use the the
saw how to saw the wood right so you g
to start breaking it on your knee and
you know hope that it's going to be even
and nice no it it doesn't work like this
that's a that's a good metaphor
yeah um yeah like for me personally I
think yeah the major changes we already
talked about but um like learning react
first like you're you're presented with
so many options it's almost overwhelming
so I think like road map sh does a
really good job of like telling you the
different paths you can take um and it
makes you start from JavaScript so I
love that um but with react native as
well like it takes you through different
options you have um and I think there's
a shift in like
thinking on the react side and react
native side of things like they react
native had an RFC recently and it's
looking at react native as a framework
um where and then you have tools on top
of that will help that will help you
build those production level apps and I
think you know react native themselves
recommend Expo as that way of building
your react native apps and that doesn't
mean like you have to use xbo but it
does make it a lot easier so I would say
like if you're learning for the first
time like yes you can use those tools to
sort of make you know creating your
first app a little bit easier pick one
po there's so many options um when we
look at State Management for example you
know you've got like six different
options which one do you go for but I
think picking one and then sort of
working your way through the rest is a
lot easier than looking at everything
and just being like okay what do I
do yeah yeah that makes sense uh and uh
good thing that you mentioned State
Management
uh because I think we are heading to
this uh specific topic um which is like
okay so what what kind of choice we got
we got the Redux we got mobx uh Zan J
Tha recoil and uh X State I never I
never met xstate anywhere uh on a
project but I know it exists so we got
so much choice and there's also context
right I mean it's not specifically State
Management but you can use it this way
so what how do we choose one right like
if if I'm a newcomer I got all this
stuff you know people will feed me Redux
but it's just not great to learn as a
beginner so you know how do I make a
good choice uh all I know you know few
things about State Management for a
reason uh why don't you take over I have
my reason to she wrote a book guys read
the
book WR an amazing book um so sorry than
you um and I see the all the State
Management you mentioned the my book was
published last year and there's already
a few new ones that are coming up and
they're looking good like Legend State
and also Anisha showed me like the T oh
my gosh I forgot the name t Leaf yeah
yeah uh yeah uh so so I looked at that
and it looks very interesting
so uh it basically comes down to your
opinions and uh you can write a lot of
stuff you should really always start
with just your app and context and only
at the moment where you see that that is
not enough should you start looking into
something more and then um well it's a
question of preference really there's
not you there are people who maybe
create benchmarks that something works
better than something else but it's
going to be like milliseconds of
differences so we go back to what you
mentioned Kuba before which is DX and
what you feel com with what you like
using and uh so so that's that there are
uh it's categorized and we we talked a
moment before Anisha you want to touch
on that on the categories of State
Management so I think like when I was
trying to learn State Management like
the only option was Vu and I and I was
overwhelmed and I think like what what
helped me learn about the rest was yeah
like seeing what categories Things fall
into so I think like when you look at
Redux and zustan like it's more reducer
based like you know you're having act
dispatching actions to that centralized
state which is often like what people
call like the single source of Truth and
then with recall and ji it's more atom
based so state is split into like those
tiny pieces of data um which which which
people call atoms um and it can be read
and written to by the hooks and then I
think Ms and falls into like observable
state where you can track the
dependencies between the state and the
components so that's sort of like I kind
of jotted this down and I was like this
is how my brain kind of puts these
categories and I think there's an
article I read that categorizes them
into something similar but like looking
at them as those three helps you think
so if I've learned for example Redux
this then might be a bit easier to learn
or for example if I've learned recoil Jo
typ would have a similar pattern of
looking at things but I think it's
really nice that like you don't have to
learn Redux anymore and Redux from back
in the day you know it's become Redux
toolkit it's so much easier it's so much
nicer to use um I really appreciate that
yeah Redux tokit is definitely like the
way to go if anybody starts a new
project with Redux today please don't
just go like try Redux to it at least
take a look and uh besides the
categories you mentioned there's uh
there's xate that as KU mentioned as
well sort of like escapes all other
categories it's my personal favorite
when I do private projects I always use
xate because it's of it presents your
state as a state machine so you you have
to think about the states of the things
you're coding so you have a button you
have to think of the states that it can
be in and it it can be like active or uh
disabled or whatever um I like um so
again this is a personal preference I
just like it works for my brain it's
fine I like it I think it's nice all
right and as you said it it all goes
down to the opinion and you know it's
fine to have to have your own
preferences uh Anisha do you have your
favorite one yeah mine definitely is a
stand I think it's just super easy to
use and like you know the fact that it
leverages hooks you can have like your
state set up in like 10 lines of cod
which I think coming from having to set
up like Redux with you know your actions
and dispatches and you'd have like five
different files and then you'd still be
like doing like the spaghetti in your
head as to where things are coming from
yeah like it's just nice to look at and
use but I think you know the state of
react native like shows a really good
trend of like where everything's going
so if you're still confused and you
don't like our personal opinions which
you should um good to check it out like
I think react query is one of the ones
that's on the rise a lot recently yeah
like react query or like the official
name t query now that's a that's like a
very interesting um part of our world
because I find that for many devs who
have never worked with it it's difficult
to their heads around the fact that it's
not really State Management it's not
really caching but it's sort of in the
middle and I've seen many developers Who
start working with it and they try to
mix Redux with react quy kind of like
fill in holes that are not there because
react query or tquery is already doing
all that for you so if uh if you're like
starting to work with uh tack query make
sure to go through the documentation
because like there's a 90% chance that
whatever you're trying to do you're
gonna find that in the documentation and
it just it's covered there do you have
um section in your book on react query
yes I do then uh look up this source as
well uh yeah but my favorite one is uh
moex for for a change so we got all
different uh different have you have you
tried
Val no I I don't even know if I've heard
of it oh it's supposed to be like the
better mobx it's the same as zustan is
for Redux that's valo for mobex all
right I'm gonna it's created by the same
like uh po mandress so it's like a
community of
developers okay sounds interesting um
yeah and I think this is a great place
to encourage our viewers on YouTube I
suppose uh if you have your opinions
drop a comment you know it's it's all
awesome to see why people choose
specific things we all learn here uh go
on Anisha I inter I want to ask AA like
do you think that the rise in like
interest for react query comes from you
know the rise in Ser intro well the
introduction of server
components yeah definitely that's
uh I think I think so
actually well I'm not sure about the
source no I'm not sure I like my first
thought was yes but then I'm not sure if
maybe it was sort of developed
independently that uh the Ser components
so the same need as the developers of uh
react query that that this is what we
need we need a better cooperation with
the server we need better control over
cash and the data that comes in so um
yeah that's that's what I think maybe it
just happened like by chance in parallel
yeah it's possible to yeah I mean it it
looks like because um Rea quer is with
us for for some time now I don't
remember when it got popular but I
remember it's been at least at least two
years I would say yeah definitely so and
I don't know if they already had an idea
of uh several components back then uh
but yeah um okay I I think that you know
if we had the whole day we could stick
to the State Management discussion
because it sounds really cool and I feel
like I can learn a lot from you guys so
somebody if somebody who's watching
feels like doing some like history
digging in Into The Internet of Things
please leave a comment with information
if you find it that would be awesome
that would be
awesome um all right but let's leave it
here let's leave um our audience a
little hungry for knowledge so they
actually do the research right yeah um
and I would like to ask you what do you
think is the future of uh State
Management in react native what can what
it can look like um you know moving on
because I you you pointed really nicely
react query or rtk query is taking its
space right now people are starting
using it more and more and trying to
understand it deeper that's great so
what is
next maybe I will I will give it to you
yeah I mean it's I'm not good question I
think like so the way that we I would
say we have to take learnings from
probably the way State Management's
going in react and I would say like the
reason we're seeing a trend like for
example just stand and like the
minimalistic State Management libraries
is because that's sort of what people
people want um they want an easier way
to handle State Management um so I think
we'll see probably a rise and Trend in
like those minimalistic State libraries
maybe that'll be something new um I
think the fact that react server
components are becoming such a big thing
there will be probably changes in the
way that we think about State Management
like you know use the hooks don't work
if you're doing serde rendering and
that's also probably why like react
query in the react world is becoming
more and more popular because people
need a way to do server side date
management so I don't know if like that
Trend will come through to react native
but it'll be interesting to see um I I
don't like I've touched on turbo modules
and like you know the new architecture
and like my learning but seeing how for
example that the new Js bridge and like
how we interact with like native modules
I don't know enough so if anybody does
please do you know leave some comments
to like help me with my learning but
like is there is there going to be a
trend around how State Management like
works with Native modules that's just a
theoretical question
interesting yeah all right all I have
any any other thoughts on that well I
had one though when you were asking your
question because you mentioned rtk query
so I remember that there's also redx
toid query and town query so so so that
points to the fact that there is
interest in in those Solutions and
people are trying uh people behind react
toolkit a Redux toolkit they realize
that they can add this to their library
and it's great we're actually using it
in our project and then I I like using
it it's nice uh and at col we have a
thing called upskilling day so like once
a month we have a full day of trying to
learn new things and actually yesterday
we had a talk by Shimon who was speaking
about over thee updates to our to apps
where we can leverage uh service
components right am I remembering this
right because this wases like it's fresh
in my mind I'm not sure like it's not
you know it's not settled down um but
this was the first time when every time
before his talk when I saw people
talking about um server components I was
thinking like uh for react native what's
the point for react native know I that
much I'm not reading into the article
you know I'm going to spend 20 minutes
on something else but so yesterday he
planted the seed in my brain that maybe
this is something really viable for our
use cases uh for our apps and for
pushing changes to react native
apps but this is still um this is still
an idea right I mean there is uh I think
there I don't okay I don't remember
correct right now if Shimon mentioned
that but there are some Works uh like
proof of concept Works around this or
not do you remember
Ola ah we we will need to ask him
exactly I remember I remember him
explaining that when you do over the air
of course there are some problems
because you have apple that Apple
doesn't like you to update your app too
much over the year right they don't like
you to change the bundle too much but
there uh once you do those over thee
updates you can like Leverage add more
stuff if you do server components like
it's supposed to be easier and like more
straightforward mhm yeah and I think
that uh Shimon also um has talk on that
topic from uh from conference in Berlin
and I think it's online you can you can
look it up so um if possible we'll drop
the link in the notes of this episode so
everybody can check it out and learn new
things maybe we can actually settle down
our knowledge cuz from yesterday so much
information yeah yeah uh yeah but that's
that's a really really interesting
perspectives
um and uh you know the the the
the let me let me put it in in in the
right words um the way that react forget
is bringing like it's taking away the
responsibility for us to to like care
about this performance memorization
memorization and Stu like that I'm
wondering if some solutions maybe you
know not this specific because that's a
compiler right but similar approaches to
State Management if if anybody will try
to take on that so they going to build
like a solution that's going to take
care of all the State Management in our
so we don't need to care about it and we
just use it like a variables anywhere
right that'll be very simplified
approach but it sounds very tough to to
tackle that I'm just wondering if
somebody will ever have a courage to do
this I mean if you're if you're talking
about the react team I think what they
did with context was their sort of them
trying right to to dip their toe in the
s Management and I don't want to be mean
but for me it's sort of backfired
because uh you know we really had have
to know how to use it in order not to
break the performance of your app so
it's not it's not the best thing that
exists in the react World like context
is not my favorite feature of
react um it's not the most intuitive one
right I mean it's interesting take I I
like that it's just out of the box right
but yeah as you said you need to
understand how to use it otherwise
you're going to break your it is yeah
it's like I love hooks I I I use hooks
like every day at work and I I think
that feature is great and it's thought
out and it's awesome uh I'm just not a
big fan of context I think it depends I
think like people need to understand
like what to use context for and what
not to use context for I think what
happens is as a new developer like
you're probably like okay this works for
State Management you throw everything in
a context like you said like when you're
using it for something like a theme it
makes sense when you're using it to like
handle your the entire state of your
application you're probably better off
like going with the state State
Management
solution I think those like dos and
Dawns like when and when not to use
State Management maybe all we could we
could write an article or something
maybe somebody already has if you find
an article on this like please drop it
in the comments as well we we can write
a better one no way
exactly exactly uh yeah but with the
with the context it's also as you said
you can start a theme that's a great
idea when you wrap up your whole up in
this but you can also uh have do smaller
context to manage the state but then you
give up on the readability of your code
because it's just going to get messy
right so there are you know pros and
cons of everything basically but I'm I'm
very curious about the what's coming
this year in react because it seems like
react is um the the latest changes that
they announc so not react foret but
react compiler and they're supposed to
remove use memo and use call back right
sort of uh sort of hided under the hood
so react is Maybe becoming a little more
of a black box but maybe that's okay
maybe that that's that's why it's going
to be even more comfortable to use I'm
very like I feel that this year is going
to be I feel and I hope that this year
is going to bring some some big changes
like in react 18 well you know thinking
about it this way uh it makes sense of
course but it also kind of resonates
with what we were talking about before
so before react uh was not that easy to
work with and but because of that you
had to understand how to work with it
then they started taking away stuff
making things simpler and more
comfortable but giving up on the deeper
knowledge that you require you were
required to have now uh compiler takes
it takes away the knowledge of the
memorization you don't need that anymore
question is will this introduce issues
like you know will there be stuff that
we actually need to understand when
using this compiler or or will it be
like just so simple like a walk in a
park just plug it in that's it you know
so it's becoming a black box is it good
maybe it but maybe people will just not
care about details anymore and that's
not going to be great right so we'll see
we'll see I I'd like to quote my
favorite JavaScript newsletter which is
bites. devv and it's definitely like my
my favorite newsletter of all
newsletters and in the last um in the
last um newsletter they wrote that the
react compiler will will take away the
need to talk with that one teammate that
you have that thinks we should memor all
the things so we all have that one
teammate that things we should all the
things so over that's definitely a big
Pro like yeah let's do that so you can
fire that guy already no don't do that
he's actually useful uh he's useful but
we don't need to talk about memo anymore
yeah that's good take it out of the memo
um all right ladies uh let's uh we are
slowly heading towards the end of this
one and uh I H let you know what I have
to share it with our listeners
uh before when we were planning this
episode we wanted to talk about women in
Tech right that was the idea before that
but we were like you know what let's
let's talk about state of the react
because that's just interesting and and
fun because women are people
too you say it yeah you say
it I'm I'm just supporting you here I
cannot tell but uh so that was the idea
and because of that for like at the end
of the episode I would still like to ask
you um what would be your tips for you
know women looking to start um you know
making their first steps in Tech maybe
they want to start learning programming
or maybe they are on their already
Junior positions and they want to just
grow um so do you have any maybe
personal experiences or you've heard of
something that you know might be really
useful for
them uh I will give it a go for Anisha
yeah so I think the reason we didn't
want to do just a women in Tech episode
is to like we're not we're not just
women in Tech like we're just we are we
are reac native developers and we wanted
to say that we wanted to show like I
guess younger women that you don't you
you shouldn't be categorized as just a
woman in Tech like that's not our label
we all has written a book she's like one
of the leading experts I I I've learned
so much already in like probably just
the two hours we've spoken um and I
think you know that we have a lot of
knowledge to share and we want to be
able to share that as experts in the
react native field not not women in Tech
and we just thought okay fine let's just
not let's not do the usual thing and
actually show young women that you can
start from anywhere like all you started
from languages I started from
engineering like you can start from
anywhere and you can go into the tech
field and you might have a windy path
but you'll find your kind of spot and so
my advice to like anybody I wouldn't
even say like a young woman in Tech is
don't be like intimida by the depth or
the you know the MTH world out there of
like what to learn um kind of just take
your path and choose choose different
like when there's options choose one and
learn it and the best way to kind of
learn is by sharing um and in fact like
I do recognize though that there is
there is obviously
a I don't I wouldn't say problem I would
say there is H I don't even know what
the right word is but there probably
people like young women in Tech want to
see more women people that look like
them in senior position so you want to
see like how did haa end up where she is
how did I end up where I am just because
you want to see someone who looks like
you doing the thing you want to do and
so I'm really looking to share kind of
that story so I'm going to try and
record some similar to this actually
like some fireside chats with some of
the women who've inspired me in my
journey um and just see how they got to
their to their the point where they are
um so it's going to be called her code
stories and it's just going to be a
woman telling her story how she ended up
where she is um so hopefully that helps
uh learn my young women learn or want to
get into Tech um because I think the
only way to like solve a problem is to
get more people like Alla like you know
who are in these amazing positions like
right doing amazing things out there in
the open sharing the like technical work
they're doing so yeah that's my that's
my long-winded answer sorry that was a
that was an awesome answer I could like
sign with both hands uh seriously uh
what I what I would like to add is that
it is a fact that there's like there's
less women intact than maybe in other
positions but there's more and more and
uh I would recommend looking for maybe
like Role Models uh on the internet you
can like I love there's a bunch of girls
do that do tag on Twitter and that who
are hilarious and smart
and it's really fun to to look what they
look at what they write and like my my
biggest advice to anybody who wants to
get into Tech H either you're a boy or a
girl is that would not get discouraged
if you don't like the tech that you're
working with and actually Anisha like
your past is also like a proof of that
you start with something you start with
engineering but you didn't like that so
you look for something else and there's
like there's so many things even even if
you decide that you want to do web
there's like a gazillion things you can
choose from there's backend development
front full uh full stack whatever and
you can code cars or you know
refrigerators whatever there's seriously
and don't feel bad if what you're trying
to learn doesn't spark Joy it's like
like you don't have to uh you can just
switch you can try a different
technology and find something that you
do like and once you find it you'll have
fun working with
it lovely lovely what what a great set
of tips for everyone not just for women
I agree with that because I would say
the same to anyone uh maybe one more
thing I could add uh to this one uh is
if you're starting maybe not even
starting when you are even a seniors
have this problem stop I mean start
putting value on yourself like you are
your work is worth a lot and you need to
realize that when you're going for a job
interview and you know the the the money
doesn't satisfy I'm negotiate I mean you
are not there because they they don't
have any choice they do have a choice
but you know prove your value right um
don't don't uh don't end up being the
person who just took the job because you
were nice you know and don't do that um
so uh that that will be my advice at the
end um so thank you very much Anisha
thank you very much Ola it was my
pleasure to have you on this coffee talk
um I hope our audience will take away a
lot from this I feel like there were
some great tips some great discussion
sparkers and uh idea givers so let's see
let's see where it goes I hope people
will leave some comments with their
ideas with their research uh yeah we
waiting for the research on server
components come on come on internet is
do thing and if you have any you know
ideas of what you might like like what
you're going to see in 2024 like I think
all of us would love to hear I mean if
there's a way to make testing on TV
easier also just please tell me because
that is my B 2024 that is all I want to
know so I'm gonna test my TV today after
work you I'm gonna just sit down on a
couch and start
testing you can hire do the focus
management testing I actually
yes oh my God they're gonna keep me to
that at work now they're gonna
give that's going to be your LinkedIn
title she loves Focus management and
everyone's going to friend you because
that is just weird can we right can we
cut it
out I don't think so it's going
wi just kidding we shall see about this
but for now uh we're g to end this here
and uh last few words from me please
sign up people for Kack newsletter
because it is for Developers for Tech
leaders but not only also for people who
want to get in there and start coding
and get your foot in the in the door uh
there's some great content there uh
there is some blog stuff there is some
podcast stuff and others so go go ahead
and sign up
and that's it thank you very much I hope
you're going to have a great day evening
afternoon whatever time it is at your
place have it great and see you in the
next
one bye bye
[Music]
bye
no